A while back, we covered a series of
studies that indicated that we can
stabilize plaque in our arteries when we
consume omega-3 fats, like those in fish
oil, krill oil, fatty fish, algae.
Beyond that, these studies suggested
that omega-3s reduce the inflammation in
the plaque, one of the primary ways that
plaque in our arteries stabilizes. In
fact, we want more stable plaque because
it's less likely to rupture, like soft
plaque, and damage downstream blood
vessels. And part of the stability is
based on the inflammation occurring
within the plaque itself. I mean the
literal immune cells found mixed in with
the cholesterol streaks underneath the
lining of cells that make up the initial
area of the blood vessel. These immune
cells invade between that initial lining
of cells in the blood vessel and attempt
to clear out the stuck cholesterol.
However, as they become overburdened
with cholesterol, they can become
pro-inflammatory as they recruit more
immune cells to the region to help. It's
a self-perpetuating cycle with a lot of
intricacies that we won't go over now.
Just know that unstable, dangerous
plaque can be unstable because it's
bloated with immune cells. So, knowing
that and knowing that omega-3 fats helps
stabilize the plaque, I was curious, how
does it do that? Luckily, there are a
lot of studies looking at omega-3s and
cardiovascular disease with many being
mechanistic to offer some resolution to
that question. There's this uh one study
I found where the researchers applied a
variety of polyunsaturated fats like
omega-3 fats to the initial lining of
cells that I told you about, the ones
that the immune cells are trying to get
past to get to the stuck cholesterol.
That lining of cells are called
endothelial cells. And something
intriguing happens when these cells are
exposed to omega-3 fats. These
endothelial cells express or produce
different proteins much like any other
cell. But the one of these classes of
proteins is called adhesion molecules.
These adhesion molecules are then placed
in the membrane of the cell facing the
bloodstream. And it's here that binding
proteins on the immune cells will lock
onto the adhesion molecules, allowing
the immune cell a grip on the surface of
the cell. Think of it like grabbing onto
a stick sticking out with a gnarled end
as you slip through a slide. It'll stop
you from continuing your slide. From
there, the immune cell anchored on the
blood side can invade past the
endothelial cell to find itself into the
plaque. So that in mind, this is the
only datim that I'll show you because
it's the most poignant. We're looking at
VCAM, an adhesion protein produced and
trafficked to the surface of the
endothelial cells. The higher the bars,
the more VCAM adhesion protein is
present. Then we have four fats applied
to the endothelial cells. We're
concerned with DHA and EPA there. They
are our omega-3s. The black bar is a
pro-inflammatory state without any fats
added. So if the bars drop from that
one, that's a good thing. It means that
there's less adhesion protein. The
lighter the bars in shade, the more fat
has been added. Clearly, we see a dose
response reduction in VCAM 1 when
omega-3s are present, especially with
DHA known as docohexoninoic acid. So,
this offers evidence that in a strong
pro-inflammatory environment like that
seen in unstable plaque, omega-3s can
reduce the adhesion proteins that allow
immune cells to invade into the plaque.
Pretty neat, isn't it? That's one way.
But in the studies that we initially
went over, there was an elux or an
egress of immune cells out of the
plaque. So, how was that accomplished?
By the way, I'm going to link my initial
analysis going over those human studies.
But if you're interested in a deeper
dive, including more on the types of
omega-3s and even plaque reversal from
my full analysis, check out the
physiotic insiders version. It comes
with an article, uh, more details, and
you're welcome to discuss it with me in
live sessions that I do for the
insiders, plus all these perks that you
get too. The link to access everything
is in the description. I'll see you over
there. In terms of immune cell elux or
removing immune cells already present,
there's a protein called CCR7 that is
quite important to convince immune cells
to leave the plaque. Essentially, it's
produced as a receptor and that receptor
gets placed in the membrane of the cell.
That receptor then binds a few different
molecules that are secreted from nearby
cells. When these molecules make contact
with the macrofasages at the CCR7
receptor, they essentially guide it like
a plane being guided by runway lights to
the lymphatic system where the
macrofasages can then leave the blood
vessel. Honestly, I'm skipping over so
much detail that I think is absolutely
wickedly cool, but I don't want to
concentrate too much on all that right
now. I'll probably create separate
content to get some of these fascinating
mechanisms covered as well. They're
among cellular behaviors that I've never
heard of before and deserve their own
attention. The main point here is that
the greater expression of CCR7 and the
production of these guiding molecules by
lymphatic cells guides the macrofasages
out of the blood vessel thereby clearing
immune cells. There are other ways that
macrofasages can be convinced to leave
like a protein called nrin one, but we
don't need to get into all those
intricacies to know that it's possible.
Unfortunately, while we have pretty good
evidence that omega-3 fats encourage the
remodeling of plaque, and we also have
evidence that omega-3s discourage the
production of adhesion proteins
responsible for the immune invasion into
the plaque. There's little mechanistic
evidence on omega-3s and how they might
encourage this. elux or egress of immune
cells. So something that future research
will hopefully look into. So yeah, just
another nugget of cool data on how
omega-3s help us avoid worsening plaque
forming cardiovascular disease. And if
you haven't egressed out of the video
already and you're interested in more on
this very topic, invade into my deep
dive on the topic right here. I'll see
see what I did there. I use the
technical words from the video